HOW TO MAKE MOVIES WITH VPYTHON
It is not possible to make movies within VPython animations yet. Several ways were posted at this FAQ. Here is a similar method using different, and I believe simpler, free tools. The two steps are: capture the VPython images with PIL or Pillow, and string them together with FFmpeg to make a movie.
Install Python Image Library (PIL) for Python 2.7, http://effbot.org/zone/pil-index.htm
Install FFmpeg, http://ffmpeg.org/, note its path (see also my version provided below). This wiki and the FAQ may be helpful.
Capture images in your code as
    import ImageGrab    # from PIL
    ...loop...
        im = ImageGrab.grab((0,0,500,500))  # screen box from (0,0)-(500,500)
        im.save('img-xxx.png')              # save image to disk, xxx=img number, e.g. 000-200 
Make movies from the images. Open a DOS/command window, issue the following command, in the directory of the images
    ffmpeg -r 20 -i img-%3d.png -vcodec libx264 -vf format=yuv420p movie.mp4 
This will make a 20 fps (-r 20) movie from files numbered 000-max, with max=999 (%3d). Increase max to 9999 with %4d etc.

Discovered above call does not work, replace with this

ffmpeg -f image2 -pattern_type glob -framerate 12 -i 'img-*.png' -vcodec libx264 -vf format=yuv420p movie.mp4

A complete example
Here is the working source code for the bouncing ball, bounce.py. If you have "ffmpeg.exe" in the path, the program will automatically make a movie "movie.mp4". Download FFmpeg from the official site (32 bit static build is fine), or unzip the version I use (9.6 MB) (old but works) into the same folder as the Python program.
Some settings can be customized, including fps, size, clipping, html5 embeddable videos (mp4), etc. Here is a DOS batch file for customizable parameters, movie.bat.
On Mac or Linux, one needs a wrapper for ImageGrab, as pointed out by Steve Spicklemire here: To get the 'bounce.py' program to work on the Mac I had to make two changes. Apparently PIL's ImageGrab is Windows only. I found this:
    import pyscreenshot as ImageGrab
    ......
    call("ffmpeg -r 20 -i img-%3d.png -vcodec libx264 -vf format=yuv420p,scale=412:412 -y movie.mp4".split())
The pyscreenshot module claims to be cross platform (you can "pip install pyscreenshot"). The 'subprocess.call' takes a list of arguments as its first argument. On the mac at least if you pass a single string with embedded spaces it tries to find a single executable with that name (including the spaces!) which naturally fails. If I 'split' the string it appears to work.


INSTALLING FFMPEG

Install Xcode

Install Xcode from the Mac App Store.
Open Terminal, enter the following and click “accept” on the dialog box:
xcode-select --install
Using MacPorts

Get the latest MacPorts “easy installer” and install it: https://distfiles.macports.org/MacPorts/
Install FFmpeg
sudo port install ffmpeg
Using Homebrew

Install Homebrew with the following command:
ruby -e "$(curl -fsSL https://raw.github.com/Homebrew/homebrew/go/install)"
Install FFmpeg.  The command will be “brew install ffmpeg –ANY-OPTIONS-YOU-WANT”.
Example:  brew install ffmpeg --with-fdk-aac --with-tools
A couple quick notes.  You might be asking “what’s the difference between Homebrew and MacPorts?”  Well, they basically do the same thing.  Homebrew is a little easier to use, MacPorts is a little more complicated but powerful (though many would argue the point).  In truth I have just had a little easier time with MacPorts while I seem to have to wrestle a little more with Homebrew.  For instance, in this article I actually had some bugs with Homebrew I had to fight.  Conversely, the FFMPEG Project actually documents and supports Homebrew.

If there’s any interest in a “How To Use FFmpeg” post please comment!

Edit:  Here’s a list of optional installs using Homebrew

–with-fdk-aac  (Enable the Fraunhofer FDK AAC library)
–with-ffplay  (Enable FFplay media player)
–with-freetype  (Build with freetype support)
–with-frei0r  (Build with frei0r support)
–with-libass  (Enable ASS/SSA subtitle format)
–with-libcaca  (Build with libcaca support)
–with-libvo-aacenc  (Enable VisualOn AAC encoder)
–with-libvorbis  (Build with libvorbis support)
–with-libvpx  (Build with libvpx support)
–with-opencore-amr  (Build with opencore-amr support)
–with-openjpeg  (Enable JPEG 2000 image format)
–with-openssl  (Enable SSL support)
–with-opus  (Build with opus support)
–with-rtmpdump  (Enable RTMP protocol)
–with-schroedinger  (Enable Dirac video format)
–with-speex  (Build with speex support)
–with-theora  (Build with theora support)
–with-tools  (Enable additional FFmpeg tools)
–without-faac  (Build without faac support)
–without-lame  (Disable MP3 encoder)
–without-x264  (Disable H.264 encoder)
–without-xvid  (Disable Xvid MPEG-4 video encoder)
–devel  (install development version 2.1.1)
–HEAD  (install HEAD version)

